The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
We're talking about the Battle of Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
and we talked about the story of one woman.
She's Zainab Bint Al-Haris(زينب بنت حارث), who tried to poison Rasool Allah ﷺ, we talked about her story.
So, on the other side,
Let's talk about the story of Safiyyah Bint Huyaee(صفيه بنت حيئي).
Saffiyya Bint Huyaee رضي الله عنها remembers
she recalls an incident that happened while she was very young girl,
and she recalls it, she reported that when Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) from Makkah to Madina.
And he was welcomed and greeted by Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألأوس وَالْخَزرَج), the Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
She says that, whenever her father or her uncle would see her.
They would play with her and smile to her
and as you would do with the young child, beautiful child.
However, that particular day when she went, both of them were sitting under a tree,
when she went to them, she said: They didn't welcome me as they usually do.
And then I heard my uncle, asked my father and say: Is it him.?
My father said: Yes.
He said: Are you sure it's him.?
So, my uncle said: So, what are you going to do.?
He said, or what do you think about him.
He said;
عَدَاوَتُه’ وَالَلهِ مَاحِّيْتَ
I will be his enemy, as long as I live.
And Huyaee Bin Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب) did live up to this vow of his,
and he was the enemy of Rasool Allah ﷺ until he was killed.
This was at the time of Hijrah(هجرة).
Three years later, Rasool Allah ﷺ would besiege, fortresses of Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير),
the people of Huyaee Bin Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب), whom he was their leader.
And they would be evicted.
So, they would move to Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
Safiyyah(صفيه) at the time, was a young girl.
Then following that, in the fifth year of Hijrah(هجرة), it is Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب),
who convinces the third and last tribe of the Jews in Madina Bannu Quraidha(بنُوْ قُرَيْظَه) to betray Rasool Allah ﷺ
and break the contract that they had,
this contract that Rasool Allah ﷺ had with the Jews, from the time he entered into Madina.
He is the one, who convinced them to betrayal Rasool Allah ﷺ and commit this treason.
And we know the story, they were defeated and they were all executed, including Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب).
Safiyyah(صفيه) grew up in Khaybar(خَيْبَر), and she ended up marrying one of her cousins,
Kananah Ibn Abi Al-Haqiq(كنانه إبن ابي الحقيق).
And now, Rasool Allah ﷺ defeated the people of Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
and the agreement between him and them was that,
that all of their properties confiscated by the Muslims,
and that they are to leave Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
So, gold, silver, women, children, land, houses, all of this is transferred into the hands of the Muslims.
But the Jews than pleaded with Rasool Allah ﷺ to allow them
to remain in Khaybar(خَيْبَر) and serve as workers, farming and cultivating the land.
And the narrator of the story says;
وَكَانُوْلَا يَفْرَغُوْنَ اَنْ يَقُوْمُوْا عَلَيْهَا
He said that the Sahabah(صحابه), did not have time to take care of the lands, themselves.
So, what would happen is if the Jews leave, these lands would stop producing
because nobody's taking care of them.
Why? Because the Sahabah(صحابه) were busy with Ilm(علم), knowledge, Da'wah(دعوة), calling to Islam
and Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed.
And the terms of the agreement were, that they would remain in Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
and the harvest would be split in half.
And he told them, that they should not conceal anything from him.
All of the currency that is in their possession needs to be handed over to the Muslims
and they are not conceal anything and they agreed.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, that if we find out that you have concealed anything,
then we will punish you as we see fit and we are free from all obligations.
They agreed to that, when they handed over their property to Rasool Allah ﷺ, it was missing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had some inside information
about treasure that was taken by Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب) from Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) to Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
So, he asked them, he said: Where is the treasure of a Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب)?
So, Kananah(كنانه) said;
اَذْهَبَتْهُ الْحُرُوْبْ وَالنفقاتْ
It was spent on war, and provisions.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اَلْعهَد قَرِيْبْ وَالْمَالْ اَكْثَرْ مِنْ ذَالِكْ
This money couldn't have been spent, because it's a large amount of money,
and this happened just recently.
Kananah(كنانه) insisted that there's nothing left.
And that particular money, that belong to Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب) was spent.
But there was an old Jew, who said;
I've seen Huyaee Ibn Akhtab(حيئي إبن أخطب) roaming around in this particular area, an area where nobody lives, Kharbah(خربه).
So, when the Sahabah(صحابه) dug in that particular area, they found part of the money.
They found some of it, some of this treasure,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ told Kananah(كنانه): Where's the rest of it, Kananah(كنانه) refused to admit.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ handed him over to Az-Zubair Bin Awaam(زبير بن عوام).
وَقَالَ عذّبْه’ حَتَّى تَستأصلْ مَا عِنْدَه
Rough him up until you take what is left.
So, Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام) was able, in the end to extract information about where this treasure is located, the rest of it.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that Kananah(كنانه) be executed, and he was.
And Kananah(كنانه) is the husband of Safiyyah رضي الله عنها .
Safiyyah(صفيه) was among the captives,
and Dah'yah Al-Kalbi(دحية اَلْكَلْبِي) one of the Sahabah(صحابه).
He came to Rasool Allah ﷺ asking for a slave.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ handed him over Safiyyah(صفيه),
because that was the rule at that time in the world,
this is not something that the Muslims brought,
that's the way things were.
Muslims came, on the international scene and this is how it was,
that women and children, if they fall into custody after war,
they are automatically enslaved.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him go and choose a woman, that you like,
so he went and he, and he took Safiyyah(صفيه).
She was described as being very beautiful so, he ended up choosing her.
So, one of the Sahabah(صحابه) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him
that Dah'yah(دحية) has taken Safiyyah(صفيه), the daughter of the noble man of Al-Yahood(اليهود),
and she is only be fitting to be yours, O Messenger of Allah.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ called Dah'yah(دحية) and told him;
Hand over Safiyyah(صفيه), and go and take someone else.
Dah'yah(دحية) did so.
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he saw Safiyah رضي الله عنها .
He offered her freedom as Mahar(مهر), and he would marry her.
So, he did not take her as a slave.
But he freed her and married her, so she is counted as a wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ, and not a woman who is in bondage.
She was not,
مِمَّا مَلَكَتْ يَمِيْنُه
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw some blue marks in her face.
He asked her, What is this.?
She said: One day I was sleeping.
My head was in the lap of my husband
and I saw a dream.
I saw the moon falling in my lap.
When I woke up I told my husband about this dream.
My husband slapped me, in the face and said;
You desire the king of the Arabs.
So, Kananah(كنانه) interpreted this dream to mean, that she is desiring to marry Muhammadﷺ.
It wasn't a desire that she had,
this is a dream, that is true dream, it is from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and it is telling her, what will happen in the future,
and it happened, as it was interpreted that she would marry Muhammadﷺ.
So, those blue marks in her face, where the traces of the slap from her husband Kananah(كنانه).
Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه, he narrates to us part of the story of Safiyyah(صفيه).
And there's, this particular part that I found interesting
and it gives us a glimpse into the private life of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and how he used to deal with his family.
The camel is pretty tall animals,
so when a person is sitting on a camel, he is quite high,
it's higher than riding on a horse.
So, when people would ride on a camel, the camel must be sitting down, but even then, it's still a bit high.
Anas Ibn Malik(اَنَس ابن مالك) said: I saw Rasool Allah ﷺ sit down on the ground,
with his foot on the ground and then he raised up, his knee
and told Safiyyah(صفيه) to step with her foot on his knee, in order to climb the camel.
So, I'm sure you can sense the humbleness and the kindness and compassion that Rasool Allah ﷺ had,
he being as described by the Yahood(يهود) the king of the Arabs,
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused Kingdom,
he was offered to be a Nabi(نبي) and king and he just chose to be a Nabi(نبي) only.
Rasool Allah ﷺ the greatest of human beings,
the greatest man that ever set foot on this earth.
He sits down on the ground and has his wife step over him,
in order to climb that camel.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to soften the hearts of Safiyyah(صفيه),
because naturally Safiyyah(صفيه), her father was killed, her uncle was killed,
and her husband killed, all by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and she saw the complete annihilation of her people,
the eviction of them from the Arabian Peninsula.
All of these events occurred in front of her eyes during her lifetime and she was a young woman at the time.
So, she must have had some hard feelings because of that.
And she said;
وَكَانَ رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منْ اَبْغَضَ النَّاسَ الَيْه
Rasool Allah ﷺ was the most despised of people to me.
He killed my husband, and my father.
فَمَا زالَ يَعْتَذر إلي
And he would apologize to me and say;
اِنَّ اَبَاكِ علب عَلَيَّ الْعَرَبْ وَفَعَلَ وَفَعَلْ حَتَّى ذَهَبَ ذَالِكَ مِنْ نَفْسِيْ
And he continued apologizing to me, and telling me
that your father is the one, who mobilize the Arabs against me,
and he's the one, who did so and so, and he did this and that
until, all of the pain in my heart was taken away.
And this is how Rasool Allah ﷺ won the heart of Safiyyah رضي الله عنها,
she is Umm-Ul-Mo'mineen(إم المؤمنين), may Allah be pleased with her.
This is the story of Safiyyah(صفيه).
Another incident that occurred,
there was a servant of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He was struck by an arrow and he died,
so the Sahabah(صحابه) said;
اَلشَّهِيْد، اَلشَّهِيْد،هَنيئا له بِشَّهَادَةْ
Congratulations on dying as a martyr.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
كَلَّا وَالَّذِيْ نَفْسِيْ بِيَدِهْ، اِنَّ الشَمْلَة الَّتِيْ اَصَابَهَا يَوْمَ خَيْبَرْ لَمْ تُصِبْهَا الْمَقَاسِمْ لَتَشْتَعِلُ عَلَيْهِ نَارًا
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No,
by the name of the One, Whom my soul is in His hands.
The cloak that he has taken on the day of Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
from the Ghaneemah(غنيمه) is burning on him, flames.
And this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
So, that cloak is burning him, a single piece of cloth that was taken from the Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
This is a Muslim, a Mo'min(مؤمن), a Mujahid(مجاهد)
and a person who died Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
but Rasool Allah ﷺ refused to pray Janazah(جنازه) for him
and he said: No, he's not a Shaheed(شهيد).
Why?
Because of that cloak that he has taken.
So, this is how dangerous it is to take anything from Al-Ghaneemah(ألغنيمه).
Also in the Battle of Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
when the Muslims were laying siege to some of the fortresses,
they were very hungry,
so they ended up slaughtering donkeys and cooking them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, What is boiling in these pots?
They said;
حمر الاهلية
We slaughtered some donkeys.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Throw it all away,
and that is when, Rasool Allah ﷺ made the eating of the flesh of donkeys, Haraam(حرام).
It was something, that the Arabs would do before that but Islam made it Haraam(حرام).
So, it's not allowed to eat the flesh of donkeys.
It was made Haraam(حرام) during the Battle of Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
The Jews remained in Khaybar(خَيْبَر) serving in the land
and the Muslims would send someone, to collect the 50% of the harvest.
So, once Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) is the one, who went to them.
So, they tried to bribe him,
and this shows you, the corruption of Al-Yahood(أليهود).
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) was very rough with them, when they did this
and he made it clear to them,
that I would not betray the trust of Rasool Allah ﷺ
no matter what you try to do, no matter what you give me.
They remained in Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
until the time of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه when he was Khalifah(خليفه).
Al-Miqdaad(المقداد) and Az-Zubair(الزبير) and Ibn Umar(ابن عمر), they went to Khaybar(خَيْبَر) to collect their shares
and the Yahood(يهود) attacked Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) at night
and they pushed him from a roof, he was sleeping on a roof,
they pushed him and he fell down and he dislocated both hands.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه said;
O people, he is speaking to the Muslims.
He said: O people, the Messenger of Allah had an agreement with the Jews of Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
that we should evict them if we wished.
So, the agreement that I had with them is that you stay and you serve in the farms.
However,it's up to us, whenever we want to evict you, we can evict you.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: O people;
The Messenger of Allah had an agreement with the Jews of Khaybar(خيبر)
that we should evict them if we wished.
They have attacked Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) and dislocated his hands, as you have learned,
having attacked one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار) before him.
We have no doubt, that it was they who did it.
We have no enemies here, besides them.
Those who have property at Khaybar(خَيْبَر) should proceed to them,
I'm going to evict the Jews.
And they were forced to leave and they went to Ash-sham(الشام).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), one of the reasons that he did this is
the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ  that no two religions should exist in the Arabian Peninsula
and the Hadith(حديث) drive the Jews and the Christians out of the Arabian Peninsula
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) even though he didn't hear this Hadith(حديث) directly from Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he investigated it and found it to be authentic and true.
And he acted upon it, and drove the Yahood(يهود) of Khaybar(خَيْبَر) out of the Arabian Peninsula to Ash-Sham(الشام).
300 years later, these Yahood(يهود), their descendants, who were in Ash-sham(الشام)
they wrote up a document
stating that, this was an agreement between them and Rasool Allah ﷺ that, they are Jizya(جزية) free.
They don't have to pay Jizya(جزية),
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), he says;
And this document has fooled, some of the scholars to believe it
and I have investigated it and found it, to be a lie and a fabrication.
There was no such document, and the Jews, and this is 300 years later.
I mean they didn't give up 300 years later and they're still fabricating
and claiming that Rasool Allah ﷺ had an agreement with them that, they shouldn't pay any Jizya(جزية).
So, the document was proven to be a fabrication.
Then 700 years after Hijrah(هجرة),
they come up with the same document again,
with some, probably with some alterations, and some changes and again it was proven to be a lie.
While Rasool Allah ﷺ was at Khaybar(خَيْبَر) he received four delegations or envoys.
The first was Wafd Al-Ashriyeen(وفد ألأشعرين).
Al-Asharieen(اَلْأشعرين) are people from Yemen from the area of Zabeed(زبيد), on the coast of the Red Sea
and will read what Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبومُوسى الأشْعَري) says in this Hadith(حديث) from Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري).
عن أبي موسى قال بلغنا مخرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ونحن باليمن فخرجنا مهاجرين إليه
أنا وأخوان لي أنا أصغرهم أحدهما أبو بردة والآخر أبو رهم
إما قال بضعا وإما قال ثلاثة وخمسين أو اثنين وخمسين رجلا من قومي
قال فركبنا سفينة فألقتنا سفينتنا إلى النجاشي بالحبشة فوافقنا جعفر بن أبي طالب
فأقمنا معه حتى قدمنا جميعا فوافقنا الني صلى الله عليه وسلم حين افتتح خيبر
Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari رضي الله عنه said;
We heard the news of the Prophet Muhammadﷺ while we were in Yemen.
So, we went out to migrate to him, me and two brothers of mine and I was their youngest,
along with 52 or 53 men from my people.
So, this was quite a large group,
they were all going Hijrah(هجرة) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
when they heard the news of Muhammadﷺ.
They took a boat, but this boat went off course and they ended up not in Madina
but in Abyssinia, the land of An-Najashi(أنجاشي),
so we found Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) there.
Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) told us that he has instructions to remain there.
So, he was staying there according to the instructions of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and we stayed with him, until we came together with Jafar(جعفر), when Rasool Allah ﷺ, opened Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
So, the next delegation then, or the next group is Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب),
the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) of Al-Habasha(ألحبشه).
Why did the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) of Al-Habasha(ألحبشه) returned back.?
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) says;
بَعَثَ الرَسول عمْرو بِنْ اُمَيَّه اَلضمَّرِيْ اِلَى النَّجَاشِيْ يَطْلُبْ مِنْهُمْ مِن بَقِي من اَصْحَابِي بِالْحَبَشَهْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Amr Bin Umayyah Ad-Damri(عمرو بن أمَيَّة اَضّْمْرِيْ) to An-Najashi(أنجاشي)
asking him, to send the remaining companions back to Madina.
Ash'habi(أشبِعي) says, that when Jafar Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) arrived at Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
Rasool Allah ﷺ kissed him on his forehead, and embraced him,
and this is what our scholars used as evidence of the permissibility of hugging, it is this incident.
This is Mursil(مُرْسَلْ) .
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَا اَدْرِيْ بِاَيِّهِمَا اَنَا اَثَرْ بِفَتْحِ خَيْبَرْ، اَمْ بِقُدُوْمِ جَعْفَرْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I don't know which has brought me more joy,
the opening of Khaybar(خَيْبَر) or the arrival of Jafar(جعفر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was extremely happy with the arrival of Jafar Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه,
it has been a long time, since he last saw, his cousin Jafar Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه.
We carry on with the Hadith(حديث) of Bukhari(بخاريْ) which we were reading from,
narrated by Abu Musa(ابوموسى).
وَكَانَ اُنَاسٌ مِّنَّ النَّاسِ يَقُوْلُوْنَ لَنَا يَعْنِيْ لِاَهْلِ السّفِيْنَهْ سَبَقْنَاكُمْ بِالْهِجْرَةْ
And some people used to tell us, We, the People of the boat
that we have made Hijrah(هجرة) before you.
وَدَخَلَتْ اَسْمَآءُ بِنْتِ عمَيْس وَهيَّ مِمَّنْ قَدِمَ مَعَنَا عَلَى حَفْصَه زَوْجَ النَّبِيْ صلى الله عليه وسلم
Asma Bint Omais(أسماء بنت عميس), who was one of the women,
who were the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) in Abyssinia,
she visited Hafsa(حفصه), the daughter Umar(عُمَر), the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, he came in and he saw this woman with his daughter, Hafsa(حفصه),
so when Umar(عُمَر) saw Asmaa(أسماء), he said;
مَنْ هَذِه
He said: Who is this woman.?
Hafsa(حفصه) said: Asma Bin Omais(أسماء بنت عميس).
Umar(عُمَر) said;
آلْحَبَشِيَّه هَذِهْ، آلْبَحْرِيَّهْ هَذِهْ
Is this the Abyssinian woman, is this the seafaring woman?
Asmaa(أسماء) said: Yes.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
سَبَقْنَاكُمْ بِالْهِجْرَه فَنَحْنُ اَحَقْ بِرَسُوْل الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مِنْكُمْ
We have made Hijrah(هجرة) before you, therefore we have more right over Rasool Allah ﷺ then you.
Meaning Rasool Allah ﷺ was closer to us or we have more right to him, then you.
Asmaa(أسماء) was quite angry with this,
and she said: No,
كَلَّا وَالله كُنْتُمْ مَعَ رَسُوْلِ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يُطْعِمُ جَائِعَكُمْ، وَيَعِظُ جَاهِلَكُمْ،
وَكُنَّا في دَارِ، أَوْ في أَرْضِ البُعَدَاءِ البُغَضَاءِ في الحَبَشَةِ، وَذلكَ في اللهِ وفي رَسولِهِ
She said: No, in the name of Allah, you were with Rasool Allah ﷺ, he was feeding the hungry among you,
and he was advising the ignorant among you,
and we were in a land that was disliked, and far away,
and all of that was for the sake of Allah and the Messenger of Allah.
وَاَيْمُ الله لَا أطْعَمُ طَعَامًا وَلَا أشْرَبُ شَرَابًا حَتَّى اَذْكُرَ مَا قلْتَ لِرَسُوْلِ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
And in the name of Allah, I'm not going to eat anything,
and I'm not going to drink anything,
until I tell Rasool Allah ﷺ, what you said;
وَنَحْنُ كُنَّا نُؤذى وَنُخَافْ
And we were harmed, and we were in a state of fear.
وَسَاَذْكُرُ ذَالِكَ لِنَّبِيِّ صلى الله عليه وسلم وَاَسْئلُه’ وَاللهِ لَا اَكْذِبُ ولَا اَزيْغُ وَلَا اَزِيْدُ عَلَيْه
And I'm going to tell him the truth, exactly.
I'm not going to add anything or subtract anything from what you said.
So, she went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and she told him
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said, so and so, said this is that,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her and what did you say?
And she mentioned to Rasool Ullah, what her response was.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ say?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
No, He does not have more right over me, then you do.
He and his companions, have one Hijrah(هجرة) and you have two Hijrah(هجرة).
Because the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) of Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه), they made Hijrah(هجرة) to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه)
and they made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told her; They have, the reward of one Hijrah(هجرة)
and you have the reward of making Hijrah(هجرة) twice.
Asma Bint Omais(أسماء بنت عميس) said: After that I would see groups and groups
of the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) who were in Abyssinia, coming to me,
asking me, to narrate to them the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And she said;
Nothing was more beloved to them in the world, than the words of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they were so happy, with this reward that came to them from the tongues of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that everybody else has reward of one Hijrah(هجرة)
while they have the reward of Hijrah(هجرة) twice
that they would come in groups asking her to narrate the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Ullah to them
and she said;
And I would remember, Abu Musa Al-Ashaari(ابوموسى ألأشعري) visiting me again, and again asking me to narrate the Hadith(حديث) to him.
He wasn't satisfied with hearing it once,
he wanted to hear it once and twice and thrice
to hear the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ that gave them, this great Ajr(أجر).
Brothers and Sisters,
we should love the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and we should love to hear it again and again, just like Abu Musa Al-Ashaari رضي الله عنه did.
He had probably travel and he had to come, a long way to listen to this Hadith(حديث), from Asmaa(إسماء).
We have the books of Hadith(حديث) with us.
All of them, right next to us, at our fingertips.
We should listen to the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
we should bless our ears with listening to the words of Rasool Ullah صلوات لله وسلام عليه.
Then there was the delegation of Addari'een(ألداريين).
Addari'een(ألداريين) were from Ash-Sham(ألشام) from the tribe of Laham(لحم).
They visited Rasool Allah ﷺ
while he was in Al-Khaybar(خَيْبَر) among them was Tamim Ad-Daari(تميم ألداري).
If you remember Tamim Ad-Daari(تميم ألداري), we talked about him in the series about the hereafter.
Tamim Ad-Daari(تميم ألداري) is the one who narrated to Rasool Allah ﷺ his story with Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
When they were in the sea and the winds carried them away to this island
and they went to this island and they found this beast covered with hair,
they cannot tell the front of it, from the back
and they went into this temple and the saw, this huge man chained up
and he asked him some questions and then he said, that he is Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
This is the one, Tamim Ad-Daari(تميم ألداري) who told Rasool Allah ﷺ, this story.
And then there's the largest delegation, which was the Wafd(وفد) of Ad-Daus(ألدوس).
Daus(دوس) are tribe from Yemen from Al-Azd(ألازد)
and these are the people of Abu Huraira رضي الله عنه,
Abu Hurairah(ابو هريره) is the one, who narrated to us the story, he said: 50(Fifty)
ثَمَانِيْنَ بَيْتَا مِنْ دَوْس
50 houses or 50 families Allah Ho-Alam(الله اعلم) from Daus(دوس),
they made Hijrah(هجرة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they arrived at Madina
but they were told that Rasool Allah ﷺ was in Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
Abu Huraira رضي الله عنه said: Wherever, Rasool Allah ﷺ is, we'll go to him.
They didn't want to wait, until Rasool Allah ﷺ comes back.
They said: Wherever he is, we'll go.
So, Saba Bin Ar-Fatah Al-Ghaffari(صبا بن عرفطه ألغفاري) who was appointed Ameer(أمير), on Madina provided them with provisions.
So, they traveled and met Rasool Allah ﷺ in Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
And therefore we can know from this,
that Abu Hurairah(ابو هريره) and Abu Musa Al-Ashaari(ابوموسى ألْأشعري) joined, Rasool Allah ﷺ at that particular time.
This is an important thing for, the scholars of Hadith(حديث), and the scholars of fiqh(فقه)
because it tells them the date in which these two Sahabah(صحابه) who narrated many Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Ullah,
it tells them when they became Muslim,
so they would know that the Hadith(حديث) that are narrated by them
are Ahadith(احاديث) that were heard, after the seventh year of Hijrah(هجرة).
On their way back, Rasool Allah ﷺ told Bilal(بلال) to wake them up for Fajr(فجر).
Bilal(بلال) overslept and so did Rasool Allah ﷺ and so did the rest of the Sahabah(صحابه).
They only woke up, due to the heat of the sun.
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ woke up and he was the first among them to wake up.
He told Bilal(بلال), what happened to you?
Bilal(بلال) told him, the same thing that happened to you.
They prayed then, and Rasool Allah ﷺ said, that,
مَنْ نَسِيَ صَلَاةْ فَلْيُصَلِّيهَا اِذَ ذكَرَهَا
When you forget about the Salah(صلاة) pray it, when you remember it.
Same thing, if you sleep then you pray when you wake up.
It's not like some people do if they missed Fajr(فجر),
they would not pray it, when they would wake up
and rather they would combine it, with the Fajr(فجر) of the next day.
That is not the correct thing to do,
the correct thing to do is to pray it, as soon as you wake up, with every Salah(صلاة).
Whether it is Zohar(ظهر), Asar(عصر), Maghrib(مغرب), Isha'a(عشاء), if you sleep, then you pray it as soon as you wake up.
Also another event occurred, while they were on their way back.
They came on top of this mountain then, there was this valley beneath them.
So, they started making Zikr(زكر) loudly,
Allah O Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah O Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah O Akbar(الله اكبر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
اِرْبِعُوا عَلَى اَنْفُسِكُمْ يَااَيُّهَاالنَّاسْ اأربعوا على أنفسكم،
فإنكم لا تدعون أصم ولا غائباً، إنما تدعون سميعاً بصيراً
O people restrain yourselves, you're not calling one, who is deaf or one, who is far away,
but you are calling the All Hearing and the All Seeing
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ saw Abu Musa Al-Ashaari(ابوموسى الأشعري) and he was saying,
he was making Zikr(زكر) in his heart,
he was saying;
لَا حَوْلَ وَلَا قُوَّتَ اِلَّا بلله
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
يَا عَبْدَالله بِنْ قَيْسْ قُل لَا حَوْلَ وَلَا قُوَّة اِلَّا بِاللهَ،فَاِنَّهَ كَنْزُ مِّنْ كُنُوْز ِالْجَنَّةْ
Say;
لَا حَوْلَ وَلَا قُوَّة اِلَّا بِاللهَ
because it's a treasure from Paradise.
So, brothers and sisters we should say;
لَا حَوْلَ وَلَا قُوَّةَ اِلَّا بِاللهَ
If you want to own a treasure in Jannah(جنة).
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to make us the people of Jannah(جنة).
These were the Muslim delegations that Rasool Allah ﷺ received
and then there was one, which was a different case.
And these were from the people of Fazarah(فزارة) from Ghatafaan(غطافان)
these were the allies of the Yahood(أليهود)
and Oyayina Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن), he saw a dream,
he saw that he's taking a mountain called Zur-Ruqaibah(ذوالرقيبة).
He interpreted it, to mean that he would hold on
because, Ar-Raqaibah(الرقيبة) was a small form of Raqabah(رقببة),
Raqabah(رقببة) means neck.
So, he interpreted it, to mean that he would take hold of the neck of Muhammadﷺ and defeat him.
So, he mobilize his people, when he heard that the Muslims have attacked Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
and he came forth to give assistance to his allies Al-Yahood(أليهود).
By the time he reached, Rasool Allah ﷺ has already conquered Khaybar(خَيْبَر) and defeated the Yahood(يهود).
So, this Oyayina Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن) he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him,
hand me over the wealth of my allies
because I took a neutral stand and did not fight you.
I mean, look at this liar, he is now saying that I chose not to fight you.
That was not the reason, he came and it was all over.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
You are a liar you came because of the screaming that you heard in your dreams.
Oyayina Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن) said: Give me something.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Go and take the Zur-Ruqaibah(ذوالرقيبة),
he said: What is Zur-Ruqaibah(ذوالرقيبة).?
He said the mountain that you saw in your dream.
I mean this is a barren dry mountain in the middle of nowhere.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Go and take it.
Oyayina Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن) left angrily, empty handed
and then he met another leader from his people called Al-Haris Bin Auf(ألحارث بن عوف).
Al-Harris(الحارث) told Oyayina(عيينة);
Didn't I tell you, that you wasting your effort for nothing.
Muhammadﷺ will conquer the east and the west.
I was told that by the Rabbi's of the Jews.
They told me that, they see this in their books
that, they would be defeated by Muhammadﷺ.
Didn't I tell you that.
So, Al-Haris Bin Auf(ألحارث بن عوف) had more wisdom than Oyayina Bin Hasan(عيينة بن حصن)
and both of them were chiefs of the people of Ghatafaan(غطافان).
We'll talk about Al-Hujjaj Bin Allaat(ألحجاج بن علاط).
Al-Hujjaj Bin Allaat As-Sulami(ألحجاج بن علاط اَلسُّلَمِيْ),
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) became Muslim,
and he belongs to the tribe of Bannu Sulaim(بنو سُلَيْم).
And he owned as it says in the books of Seerah(سيرة).
He owned the rights of mining in the land of Sulaim(بنو سُلَيْم).
Now, here mining most likely Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) would refer to the salt mines,
don't think there were any, anything, more developed than that,
it wasn't known in the Arabian Peninsula that, they used to mine for anything else.
So, this is referring to the rights of salt mining in his area.
So, he was a businessman, he was a wealthy man and he had a wife in Makkah.
When he became Muslim, he wanted to collect the money
that was owed to him in Makkah
as a businessman, he would have contracts with a lot of people and they owed him money,
so he wanted to get his money back, before the news spreads that he has become Muslim.
And he was worried that they would confiscate his money.
So, he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said; O Messenger of Allah that people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) owe me money
and I want to go and collect it, would you allow me to speak against you, if I need to.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُلْ مَا بَدَلَكْ
Say whatever you want.
So, Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) went into Makkah
and this was during the time of Ghazwat-Ul-Khaybar(غزوة الخيبر).
So, he reached to the outskirts of Makkah
and he already found some men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) outside of Makkah(مكه)
waiting for travelers to come in order to ask them about what happened with Rasool Allah ﷺ, in Khaybar(خَيْبَر)?
They were so eager to know the news of this conflict.
It wasn't like a given for them,
they expected that the Muslims would lose because of the fame of Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
its fortresses, the fighters, the provisions.
Because it was a wealthy area, they had a lot of farms,
they had many fortresses, well built, strong fortresses,
plus the strongest fighters among Al-Yahood(أليهود), such as Marhab(مرحب) and Yaser(ياسر),
the knights of the Jews were from Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
So, these men would go out during the daytime and wait for the travelers, for the caravans,
in order to ask them, what is happening?
Quite different than how things are today, all news are within reach of the whole globe, within seconds.
With them in the Arabian Peninsula, news would take days to travel.
So, they saw Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج), they knew him because he had a wife from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, they said: This is the man we're looking for, he must have information about what has happened.
So, they rushed towards Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) and they told him tell us about Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
What happened?
He said: I have some very good news for you.
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) said: They came to me and they were stuck to my camel.
I mean, you can imagine the scene of him, riding on his camel,
and these men are so crowded around him, to hear what he has to say that, they were stuck to his camel
and they're all looking up at him.
And then they're going ee, ee, Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج), go ahead Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج), just tell us.
He said Muhammad(محمد) has been defeated
as he has never been defeated before
his companions were killed.
And he was taken as prisoner.
And the Jews said;
We're not going to kill him, but we're going to hand them over to his people in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
so that they kill him inside Makkah.
The enemies of Allah happy, they rushed back to Makkah to carry the news.
And Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) told them, the only reason, why I came here is
I want to collect my money from you,
so that I can go back to Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
and buy the booty that the Yahood(يهود) won from the Muslims
before all of the other businessmen arrive to Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
and compete with me.
Because after war, there's going to be a lot of spoils of war,
and there's going to be a market, where all of that stuff will be sold.
So, I want to be the first in order to buy, what I can, before the prices go up.
They said, Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) don't worry, we're going to collect your money for you.
And they rushed back to Makkah,
doing his work for him collecting his money.
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) went to his wife and he told her the same thing as he told these disbelievers
because she was still a Kafir(كافر), herself.
And the news spread all over Makkah.
The disbelievers were in joy and the Muslims were in a state of depression.
The news reached to Al-Abbas Bin Mut'talib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) who was Muslim
and he was so, devastated by the news
that he could barely stand up and he sent one of his slaves to go to Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) and tell him;
What is this news, what is this evil news that you brought?
The promise of Allah is better for you!
So, this slave came in to Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) and conveyed to him the message from Al-Abbas(العباس).
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) told him go back,
and tell your master that I have some good news for him,
but he must wait for me in one of his houses alone and I will come and meet him.
So, the servant went back to Al-Abbas(العباس) and conveyed the message to him.
Al-Abbas(العباس) was so happy that he jumped up and kissed him and his forehead and said, You are free!
اَعْتَقتُك
He freed his slave. He was, so happy about this news.
So, you can imagine, dear brothers and sisters
the state of Ghurabaa(غرباء), the state of loneliness, and strangeness that these few Muslims who were living in Makkah, were going through.
They're living within the community that is leading the war against the Muslims.
They're living among Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and they're feeling strange.
They're feeling the pressure of the Society of Kuffr(كفر) around them.
So, you can see how following news for them, wasn't a detached thing.
It has so much effect on them.
Here, you see, it says in this narration that he was barely able to stand up.
That is because he heard the bad news about the Battle of the Muslims.
And now when you heard the good news, he jumped up
and he kisses his slave and tells him;
you are free.
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Mut'talib(اَلعباس بن عبدالمطلب ) waited for Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) to come
and Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) came and told him;
Abul Fadhal(أبوالفضل), the news is not like, what you heard?.
The reality of the situation is, that Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims have defeated the Jews,
and they have conquered their land,
and they are dividing the spoils of war amongst them.
And Muhammadﷺ has chosen the daughter of their king to be his wife.
And the only reason why, I said otherwise is,
because I wanted to get my money,
because I was worried that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would confiscate it from me when they know that I'm Muslim.
Now, Al-Abbas(العباس) give me three days.
Keep this secret for three days, and then say, whatever you want.
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) left from Makkah after he got all of his money.
And then Al-Abbas(العباس), after three days he came and visited the wife of Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) and told her;
Where's your husband?
She said: He already left.
And then, she said;
She's trying to offer her condolences to him,
because the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) they knew, even though the Islam of Al-Abbas(العباس) was secret,
but they knew that with deep in his heart, he was a Muslim and his sympathies is with his nephew.
So, she tried to offer her condolences to him. She said;
لَا يَحزُنْكَ الله يَا اَبَالْفَضَلْ’ لَقَدْ شَقَّ عَلَيْنَا الَّذِيْ بَلَغَكْ
May Allah not make you sad and the news has been very difficult on us.
He said: Yes Allah will not make me sad and Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدالله),
nothing happened but that which we like.
Allah has opened Khaybar(خَيْبَر) or allowed Muhammadﷺ, to conquer Khaybar(خَيْبَر)
and the spoils of Khaybar(خَيْبَر) are divided among the Muslims
and Rasool Allah ﷺ has chosen the daughter of their king to be his wife.
And if you care for your husband, be better follow him.
She said;
اَظنُّكَ ولله صَادِقَا
I think that you're telling the truth and she left and followed her husband.
And then Al-Abbas رضي الله عنه he put on some good clothes, special clothes,
and then he passed by the gathering places of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and when they saw him they said;
لَا يُصِيْبُكَ اِلَّا خَيْرًا يَا اَبَالْفَضَلْ
May only good befall you O Abul Fadhal(أبوالفضل).
Abul Fadhal(أبوالفضل) is his Kuniyyah(كنيه). He said;
لَمْ يُصِبْنِيْ اِلَّا خَيْرْ بِحَمْدِلله
Only good has befall me with the praise of Allah.
Al-Hajjaj(الحجاج) has told me that Khaybar(خَيْبَر) was conquered by Rasool Ullah,
and that the Muslims divided Khaybar(خَيْبَر) amongst themselves,
and that Rasool Allah ﷺ married Safiyyah(صفيه)
and he told me to keep this secret for three days,
because he only came here, to take his money from you
and then he is gonna leave you.
And now the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), suddenly the depression that was on the Muslims was transferred to the Kuffar(كفار)
and the joy that was with the Kuffar(كفار) was transferred on the Muslims, they switched places.
Al-Hajjaj Bin Aalaat رضي الله عنه tricked them.
As Malcolm X used to say they've been bamboozled.
Now, Al-Hajjaj Bin Aalaat(اَلْحجاج بن علاط) made it out, with his wealth and his wife followed him.
And then the news after that obviously reached to Makkah about the details of what happened,
and they realized that, it has been a devastating defeat for Al-Yahood(أليهود).
The stronghold, the only remaining stronghold of Al-Yahood(أليهود) in Al-Hijaaz(ألحجاز)
there were a few other small pockets of Al-Yahood(أليهود) but they would constitute no threats on the Muslims
for example there was Yahood(أليهود) in Tema'a(تيماء), and there was Yahood(أليهود) in Fadak(فدك).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ, after that signed some treaties with them
but the strongest, stronghold was Khaybar(خَيْبَر) and now it was over.
And the story of Al-Hajjaj Bin Aalaat(اَلْحجاج بن علاط) is authentic,
it's been narrated by Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) and it fulfills the requirements of Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(المسلم).
We'll talk about some Sariyyah(سرايه), some dispatches that occurred after Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
one of them was led by Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
All of the Sahabah(صحابه) would participate in Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and in going out in these Sariyyah(سرايه)
and there was a lot of activity of this sort going out throughout the year,
if one looks into this. It's really impressive at the amount of activity that was occurring,
it's amazing to see how busy the Sahabah(صحابه) were
and how much Barakah(بركة), Allah سبحانه وتعالى put in their efforts.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has been himself, he participated in about 19 battles,
there's a difference of opinion, among the scholars, some of them say 21, some of them say 19, some say 17.
And then there's about 55, Sarayah(سرايه) Special Operations, or smaller dispatches,
and all of this within the period of 10 years.
So, there was a lot of activity going on.
This Sariyyah(سريه) was led by Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and they were sent to Banni Fazaraa(بني فزارة)
and this is narrated in Muslim(مسلم) and in Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
They attack them, they ambushed them.
And Salamah(سلمة) is the one, who's narrating, Salamah Ibn Akwah(سلمه ابن أكوع) he said;
I saw them running away from us.
فَرَاَيْتُ عُنُقًا مِّنْ النَّاسْ فِيْهِ ذرِّيَهْ وَالنِسَاءْ
I saw a neck of people within them women and children,
now we're all of them women and children, or was it the mixture of men and women and children Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم).
Anyway he said: They were running away from us, and they were rushing towards a mountain,
they wanted to seek refuge in this mountain
and I was pursuing them.
فَخَشِيْتْ
I was worried that they would reach to the mountain before me,
so I took an arrow and I struck it, between them and the mountain.
So, this arrow dropped between them and the mountain.
So, Salamah(سلمة) did not want to hit them,
he didn't want to kill them, he wanted to take them as captives.
So, what he did, is he shot an arrow between them and the mountain
to let them know that they are within range
and if they don't stop, he is going to continue firing at them and he's gonna hit them next time.
So, when they saw this arrow fly in front of their eyes, they stopped,
they frozen their tracks and Salamah(سلمه), he brought all of them back to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق).
He said there was a woman, a Bedouin woman, wearing a worn out leather clothes,
and with her was a girl that was extremely attractive.
He said: Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه  gave me that girl,
so I met Rasool Allah ﷺ and when we went back to Madina,
I met Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Souq(سوق) in the marketplace
and they told me; Ya Salamah(يا سلمه),
O Salamah(سلمة) hand me over, the woman,
I told Rasool Allah ﷺ she attracts me,
اَعْجَبَتْنِيْ يَا رَسُول الله
Salamah(سلمة) liked her, she was very attractive,
so he said: She attracts me, O Messenger of Allah.
So, Rasool Allah left him and then next day, they met again in the marketplace
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told Salamah(سلمة) again.
O Salamah(سلمة) hand me over the woman,
Salamah(سلمة) told Rasool Allah ﷺ,
O Messenger of Allah, she attracts me but I will give her to you, and he handed her over to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ do with her,
he sent her to Makkah in exchange for some Muslim prisoners, who were in Makkah.
Dear brothers and sisters, Rasool Allah ﷺ was concerned about Muslim prisoners.
He says in Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاريْ)
فُكَّوا العاني
Free the prisoner and Rasool Allah ﷺ as we talked before,
he took hostages from the Kuffar(كفار) in order to exchange them for Muslim prisoners.
Rasool Allah ﷺ in this situation here,
sent this slave woman, who was very beautiful and it's going to fetch a very high price.
He sent her to Makkah in order that, they send them back some Muslims, who were taken as prisoners
and the Fuqahaa(فقهاء) say that it's a duty, it Wajib(واجب), it is mandatory on the Muslims to free their brethren from prisons.
And the Fuqahaa(فقهاء) say;
If a Muslim is taken by the disbelievers as a prisoner in the East,
then it becomes obligatory on the Muslims even in the west to spent their money to ransom him, or to free him.
So, it's the duty on Muslims.
The next Sariyyah(سريه) was led by Abdullah Bin Rawaha رضي الله عنه
and they were sent to Yusair Bir Rizaam Al-Yahoodi(اليُسَيْر بن رزام أليهودي),
This is a Jew and there were reports that he was trying to work out a deal with Fazarah(فزارة),
to attack the Muslims when they were in Khaybar(خَيْبَر),
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) to bring him,
what Abdullah Bin Rawaha رضي الله عنه did?
He went to Yusair(يُسَيْر) and he told him that Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to appoint you as governor over Khaybar(خَيْبَر).
Initially he resisted then Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) kept on, trying to convince him, until he agreed,
and he came along with 30 men 30 Yahood(يهود).
On the way back Yusair(يُسَيْر) regretted, his decision
and he tried to pull the sword of Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن أنيس).
Abdullah Bin Unais رضي الله عنه wasn't taken by surprise
and he was able to maneuver and get away from Yusair Bir Rizaam(اليُسَيْر بن رزام)
and then the Muslims saw the move of Yusair(يُسَيْر) and realized,
what he was doing?
So, every Muslim turned around to his Jewish companion
because the Muslims were 30 and Yahood(يهود) also were the same number.
So, every Muslim had the Yahoodi(يهودي) companion with him riding on the same camel.
So, now every Muslim turned around to his companion and executed him,
except one of the Yahood(يهود) succeeded in running away.
So, all of them were killed including their leader Yusair Bir Rizaam(اليُسَيْر بن رزام).
Next Sariyyah(سرية), Sariyat-Basheer Bin Saad(سرية بشير بن سعد).
They were sent in 30 men to Bani Murraa(بني مُرَّة),
in an area called Fadak(فدك).
They were surrounded by an overwhelming force
and most of them were killed,
Bashir(بشير) was injured but he was able to retreat and go back to Madina.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ because of this defeat that Bashir(بشير) and his Sariyyah(سرية) suffered
he sent out another Sariyyah(سرية) led by Ghalib Bin Abdullah(غالب بن عبدالله),
on the way they met a man called Haris Bin Malik(حارث بن مالك).
Now, this man could be a spy, he could be a traveler, Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم),
so Ghalib(غالب) ordered that he should be arrested.
Haris Bin Malik Al- Laisee(ألحارث بن مالك ألليثي), he said;
اِنَّمَا جِئْتُ مُسْلِمًا
I have come to accept Islam,
Ghalib(غالب) told him;
If you're telling the truth, and you came to really become a Muslim,
then being held a captive for a day and a night wouldn't harm you,
because they only wanted to keep him for a day.
And if you have other motives,
then we are going to take our precautions.
Because if he was a spy,
then he would disclose their location
and their numbers and would give out information to the enemy
and allow them time to mobilize their forces and gather an attack,
see these Sariyyah(سرية), they depended on the element of surprise
because they were very small in number.
And you can see that most of them were ambushes, that were done suddenly,
either at night or early in the morning.
And they take the enemy by surprise.
So, now they were spotted by this man.
So Ghalib(غالب) held him as a captive.
Now, there's a problem here, this man claims that he is a Muslim,
and it's not allowed to take the Muslim for no sin and to arrest him.
But this was the necessary move on part of the leader of the Sariyyah(سرية).
And then he tried to explain it to, this man and told him;
Listen, if you're a Muslim, it won't harm you one time, if you're arrested, if you held captive for one day,
obviously he doesn't want to take this man with them.
He had to leave him in that spot and he left with him.
It says in the narration Rajul Aswad(رجل أسود), a black man,
he gave this man instructions, he told him, if he resists, then cut off his head.
So, they had to hold him where he is, on spot, so that no information is leaked.
It shows you the Hadhar(حذر), the precautions that the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم would take,
they were very intelligent and wise, and they would not be tricked.
They carried on, and Jundub Bin Makeeth(جندب بن مكيث),
he narrates that, he was sent to scout, to spy on the enemy,
because they reached at the time of Asr(عصر).
So, Jundub(جندب), he climbed the hill, or a mountain that overlooks the enemy,
and he took a prone position, laying down stretched off the floor,
in order that the enemy would not see him.
But one of the men from among the enemy, he spotted Jundub(جندب),
now Jundub(جندب) was laying down in this position without moving.
This man saw him and he told his wife,
I see some dark object on that hill,
go and check if the dogs have taken any of our utensils.
So, she went and checked and didn't see anything missing.
She said, the dogs didn't take anything.
He said: Bring me my bow and my arrows.
So, he took an arrow and he aimed at Jundub(جندب) he shot him
and the arrow hit him.
It says, either in his Jabeen(جبين) or his Janb(جنب).
Jabeen(جبين), means forehead and Janb(جنب) means side,
the narrator wasn't sure.
Anyway, Jundub(جندب) says;
so I pulled out the arrow and put it down slowly, without making any movements.
So, the man then aimed his arrow again and short at Jundub(جندب) another time
and this time he hit him, in his shoulder.
Jundub(جندب) said: I pulled out the arrow and I placed it, put it down without moving.
So, the man said;
لَقَدْ خَالَطه سَهْمَائِيْ
My two arrows have definitely struck him.
لَو كَانَ رَبِيْعَتْ لَتَ حَرَّكْ
If, he was a scout he would have moved.
So, you can see the discipline that Jundub(جندب) had,
I mean, being struck twice by these sharp arrows, and is not moving a bit.
He is pulling them slowly, without making any noticeable movement.
So, this man was quite content and comfortable
that this object whatever it is, is not a human being.
And then he told his wife,
tomorrow in the morning, go and collect my two arrows, lest the dogs chew on them.
So, Jundub(جندب) said:, I remained in my position until, it was night time
and their camels and shepherds came back,
and then they had their dinner and they went to sleep,
and that is when we attacked,
so they attacked them, when they were asleep.
He said: We killed some of them.
And then we took all of their camels and whatever,
we took them with us and we made it, away with them.
And then the remaining men who are not killed,
gathered the force and they pursued the Muslims.
Jundub(جندب) says, that the forces that, they gathered were overwhelming huge numbers
and they were pursuing us and they were getting very close to us
and there was no way, we could fight such a number.
He said;
فَجَاؤوْنَا بِمَا لَا قِبَلَ لنَا بِهْ
They brought forces to us that we cannot handle,
he said: While we were running away from them.
We crossed a valley
there was no rain, and there were no conditions for rain.
Nevertheless, Allah brought the flood in this valley that separated us from them
and we would look back and see them all standing on the other side of the valley looking at us, unable to do anything,
and then they made it back safe to Madina.
This story of the Usama(أسامة) is also related within this Sariyyah(سرية)
and it's a famous story, you must have heard of it
and this is the story of a Usama(أسامة) with the man who said;
لَا اله الَّا الله
There was this man, whenever the enemy would attack,
he would be ahead of them and whenever, they would retreat, he would be the last,
in this Qarr(قر) and Farr(فر) process of fighting of attack and retreat,
this man was ahead in attacking and the last in retreating.
So, he was causing the Muslims some problems,
Usama(أسامة) said: Me and one man from Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), we both made it our objective to, to get him,
so we attacked and when we were within range,
he said;
لَا اله الَّا الله
So, Usama(أسامة) said: The Ansari(انصاري) stopped
and I carried on and I struck him with my sword and killed him.
The news was carried to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was angry and he told Usama(أسامة):
اَقَتَلْتَه’ بَعْدَ اَنْ قَالَ لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
Did you kill him, after he said;
لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
، قَالَ اُسَامَهْ مَا قَالَ هَا اِلَّا مُتَعَوِّذا مِنَّ السَيْفِ يَا رَسُوْلَ اللهَ
He only said it, to seek refuge from the sword.
اَقَتَلْتَه’ بَعْدَ اَنْ قَالَ لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
Did you kill him after he said;
لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
And he kept on repeating that again and again,
until Usama(أسامة) said: I wished that, I have never became Muslim, except that moment,
and then Usama(أسامة) made a vow that he will never fight anyone in his life.
Who says,
, لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
So, the important lesson here, there are two lessons.
Number one, the sanctity of Muslim blood,
it is the greatest crime after Shirk(شرك) to shed the blood of a Muslim.
And the Ayaat(آيات) of Quran and the Hadith(حديث) show us the danger
and the greatness of this sin,
the one who was murdered would come on the Day of Judgment,
and would hold on to the one who murdered him,
and will say O Allah: Ask this man, why did they spill my blood.
And there is no sin, that our scholars debated whether the Toba(توبة) is accepted or not,
except with the sin of killing a Muslim.
Now, obviously, the majority view, and the right opinion is that the Toba(توبة) is accepted.
However, it shows you
how dangerous this thing is that it reached to the level that some of them disagreed with this opinion.
So, the blood of one Muslim is sacred.
And the Hadith(حديث) says that it's more sacred than the house of Allah.
The next important lesson, Al-Akhaz Bizzahir(ألأخذ بظاهر)
we take them by what is apparent because in another narration it says,
هَلَّا شَقَقْتَ عن قَلْبِه
Why didn't you split his heart open to see what is in it?
Have you opened up his heart
to know whether he was a Muslim or not?
Whether he was honestly saying
لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
or he was saying it just to seek refuge from the sword?
How do you know?
So we go by Az'zahir(ألظاهر), we go by what we see.
If a person claims to be a Muslim, then we take him for his word,
and we leave As-Saraaer(أَلسَّرَائِرْ), we leave what is in the hearts to Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the Day of Judgment.
Now, this applies both ways,
this applies to go Kuffr(كفر) and applies to Eeman(اِيْمان),
if what we see from a person is Kuffr(كفر), then we judge them as being disbelievers.
If what we see from a person apparently is Eeman(اِيْمان) and Islam, then we judge them to be Muslim.
We did not dig into their hearts and try to find out what's in them.
Same thing here, we could also look at the lesson of Jundub(جندب),
when he took this man as a prisoner, he said,
when that man said that I'm a Muslim.
Jundub(جندب) did not try to argue with that and say you're lying, you're a spy,
No, He told him, if you're a Muslim then have Sabr(صبر) and patience for one day,
if you're not than Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم).
Next Sariyyah(سرية), Sariyyah Abi Hadrad(سرية أبي حدرد).
Abi Hazrad(أبي حدرد) got married to a woman from his people
and he promise pay a dowry of 200 Dirham(درهم).
So, he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him, O Rasool Ullah, help me,
I mean he offered to pay this Mahar(مهر) but didn't have the money,
so he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
O Messenger of Allah, I got married and I promise to pay 200 Dirham(درهم) as Mahar(مهر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
سبحان الله وَلله لَوْ كُنْتُمْ تَاخُذُوْنَهَا مِنْ وَّادٍّ مَّا زَادْ، وللهِ مَا عِنْدِيْ مَااُعِيْنُكَ بِهْ
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), if you were picking up money from a stream, you wouldn't have paid more,
in the name of Allah, I have nothing to help you with.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this as a lot of money to pay as Mahar(مهر),
and he said, if money was flowing in a stream
you wouldn't have offered to pay more than what you have paid.
Anyway later on Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد) along with two men
to go and check out what's going on with a particular man, who was gathering a force to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them:
اُخُرجُوْ اِلَى هَذَا الرَّجُلْ حَتَّى تَأتُوهُمْ مِنْه’بِخَبَرِ وَّ عِلْمْ
This man is Qais(قيس), he was gathering force to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he sent Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد) along with two men, to find out what's happening.
وَقَدَّمَ لَنَا شَارِفًا اَجْفَا
He gave us a weak old camel, and told them.
تَبَلَّغُ عَلَى هَذِه
Make do with her.
Now the situation of this camel was pretty bad, and she wasn't even working
When one of them was riding on the camel, she couldn't even stand up.
Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد) said, that we had to push it, from behind to have her stand up.
So, this camel was a very bad situation.
That's all what Rasool Allah ﷺ was able to offer them, this weak old camel.
So, they traveled three of them, with this weak camel, they arrived at night
and Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد) said: I took my position.
And I ordered my two companions to hide in another spot
and then he gave them orders, when you hear my Takbeer(تكبير), make your move.
So, he said I was waiting for an opportunity, Gharrah(غرَّه).
And no opportunity came yet.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ, His Qadar(قدر), their Shepherd was late,
shepherd of these Kuffar(كفار), he was late.
So Qais(قيس) said: I'm going to go and try to find him.
His people said, Let us go.
He said: No, in the name of Allah, No one will go with me.
They said: Then let us come with you.
He said: No, I'm going to go alone.
Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah, He walked alone looking for his shepherd
and he comes right in front of Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد).
Abu Hazrad(ابوحدرد) said: When he was within range,
I shot an arrow at him piercing him in the heart.
He said: I swear, he did not utter a sound he drop down dead without making a sound.
I jumped at him, and cut off his head.
And then I made my takbeer(تكبير) and my two companions made their takbeer(تكبير) and we attacked
and the kuffar(كفار) were in a disarray, they were running in every direction.
We took all of their camels and we made it, we went back to Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave me 13 camels.
So, I concluded my marriage.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا